<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc category="info" docName="etsn-01">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="ETSN">
    Extended TCP Service Naming
    </title>

    <author fullname="Martin Sustrik" initials="M." role="editor"
            surname="Sustrik">
      <organization>GoPivotal Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>msustrik@gopivotal.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="August" year="2013" />

    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>TCP</keyword>
    <keyword>service</keyword>
    <keyword>port</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This doucment defines a way to extend the TCP service namespace
         so that arbitrary names can be used instead of TCP ports.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title = "Introduction">

      <t>TCP ports serve double purpose. First, they uniquely identify
         a TCP connection within the scope of network interface. Second,
         they serve as symbolic names for network services, for example,
         port 80 is a symbolic name for HTTP service.</t>

      <t>While the ports are a fitting solution for the former problem,
         they are severely lacking in the latter case. Specifically, as
         we move from generic-purpose IETF-defined and IANA-registered
         services such as HTTP or SMTP to special-purpose ad hoc services,
         often limited in use to few computers, a single company or
         maybe few inter-communicating organisations the port numbers become
         increasingly insufficient.</t>

      <t>In the crowded TCP port namespace developers often choose to use port
         numbers that collide with existing IANA-registered services and even
         in the cases where they take care to choose unassigned port numbers
         the ad hoc services tend to collide each with another.</t>
  
      <t>To deal with the problem, some applications choose to use
         ephemeral ports, i.e. port numbers assigned to the application
         dynamically by the network stack from the pool of port numbers that
         are not used at the moment.</t>

      <t>Given that ephemeral ports are not known in advance, this solution
         requires an additional service to distribute the port numbers to the
         potential peers and typically results in more complex and brittle
         systems.</t>

      <t>Another problem arises if TCP service is shared among different
         organisations. Ephemeral ports are not an option in that case
         as the connections have to cross the firewalls. There's no way to open
         the port in the firewall if it is not known in advance.</t>

      <t>If, on the other hand, the ports are assigned statically the practice
         can severely hinder the development as every new service requires
         opening a new port in the firewall and thus undergoing an approval
         process that may take months in some organisations.</t>

      <t>This specification attemps to solve the problem by extending the
         TCP service namespace to arbitrary strings. At the same time all
         those services share a single fixed IANA-assigned TCP port number,
         thus reducing the administrative overhead to one-off opening of a
         single port in the firewall.</t>

    </section>

    <section title = "Connection Initiation">

      <t>When new connection is being established, the party initiating the
         connection connects to TCP port 5908 at given IP address and sends
         the following protocol header to the peer:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
+--------------+-----------+--------------+
| version (8b) | size (8b) | service name |
+--------------+-----------+--------------+ 
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The first byte is the version of this protocol and MUST be set
         to 0x01.</t>

      <t>If the version number is not equal to 0x01 the accepting party MUST
         close the underlying TCP connection.</t>

      <t>Second byte is the length of the subsequent service name. Thus,
         the service names are 0 to 255 bytes long.</t>

      <t>The assumption here is that namespace of all strings up to 255 bytes
         long is large enough to prevent service name clashes. On the other
         hand, 257 bytes (maximum size of the protocol header) is not long
         enough to be exploited in any kind of DoS attack.</t>

      <t>Note that the service name may consist of arbitrary bytes and is not
         restricted to ASCII strings or similar.</t>

      <t>If the party accepting the connection doesn't receive the entire
         protocol header within a reasonable time (e.g. 1 second) it SHOULD
         close the underlying TCP connection. This rule prevents DoS attacks
         based on opening large number of TCP connections that would linger
         around and never be handed to the user.</t>

      <t>After receiving the entire protocol header, the accepting party
         looks up the service name in its table of available services.
         If there's no corresponding service registered it MUST close the
         underlying TCP connection.</t>

      <t>Finally, if the service name is found in the table, the TCP connection
         is handed to the process that registered the service name
         in question.</t>

      <t>From that point on the connection bahves as ordinary TCP
         connection, both with respect to the data transfer and to the
         connection shutdown.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document requires that a fixed TCP port number is assigned
         by IANA for extended service naming. For now the specification is
         using port 5908.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Longer service names may provide some opportunity for DoS attacks,
         however, by limiting the service name to maximum of 255 bytes,
         the risk should be negligible.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

</rfc>

